Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today we're
going to be learning how to balance
redox reactions, specifically those
in acidic solutions or acidic mediums.
So the way that these different problems
generally always look is that you'll
be given a problem that's going to have
all these imbalanced charges on it.
And it's going to specifically tell you,
hey, you need to balance this in acidic
solution using the half reaction method.
Now when we kind of see these, these are
all about oxidation and reduction, and
they can be a very confusing problem that
can involve many steps to how to do them.
But the thing is, it's very systematic
and very procedural, meaning it's
going to follow very specific steps
when we are going to go through these.
So looking through these problems,
it's all about that oxidation
reduction, meaning it's all about
the gaining and losing of electrons.
So just remember, LEO goes
GER, and you'll remember how
to do these different problems.
and how to label them.
So in this video, we're going
to go through specific steps and
we're going to show you exactly
how to do this kind of problem.
Let's take a look.
The
problem that we're going to be working on
today is going to be the following one.
So generally the way that these
problems are written is it says
complete and balance the following
equation in an acidic solution
using the half reaction method.
Now keep in mind, acidic solution
can be worded some different ways.
It could, you could see it say
acidic medium, the same idea, or
it could say the word acidic over
the yield arrow of the reaction.
So when we're kind of looking at
this, you can't just balance it just
doing your normally your coefficients.
Um, generally, whenever it is specifically
stated to do the half reaction method,
you got to go through different steps.
Um, the only time you can ever
try to balance it is if all
the charges end up balanced.
Um, so this is a very specific method,
adding waters and hydrogens and
different types of context like that.
So we're also going to practice labeling
the oxidizing and reducing agent as well,
being that a lot of these problems ask
you to label everything on top of it.
So this tends to be the challenge
problem of a lot of exams in
general chemistry one and two.
So we definitely want to
make sure that we're able to
follow these different steps.
So let's get into doing this problem.
Okay, so this is all the specific
steps to doing this problem.
And as you can see, it is a long list
that can look very, very overwhelming.
But I thought I'd put it here
just so that we have the entire
process of how to do this.
The first thing we're going to do is we're
going to determine the oxidation numbers.
Then we'll write the half reactions.
Then we will balance all atoms
that are not hydrogen and oxygen.
Then we will balance the
oxygens by adding water.
Then the hydrogens by adding H Then
we'll balance the charges with electrons.
And then we will then go through the
half reactions combining them and
cancelling anything that is similar.
So we're going to go through this step by
step on the problem that I showed above.
Let's get into our first step,
identifying the oxidation numbers.
Okay, so the first step, determining
oxidation numbers, this is a set of
different rules that do exist for
trying to identifying these imaginary
charges that we have on these species.
So the first thing is, is just kind
of reading through them, right?
If an element by itself, it's zero.
If you have group one or two,
it follows their charges, right?
Halogens are generally negative one,
unless they're usually, if they're bound
to oxygen, then they can be positive.
Um, monatomic ions always
equal their ionic charges.
Hydrogen is always assumed to be plus
one when it's bound to a nonmetal.
Negative one if it's
bound to a net, a metal.
And then oxygen is always negative
2 unless it's in a peroxide, and
then fluorine is always negative 1.
Now the biggest thing is that the
sum of all the oxidation states has
to equal the charge of the compound.
Meaning that if you have something that's
neutral, it must be overall equal to 0.
And then if you have an actual
ionic compound, then it has
to equal the ionic charge.
So if we were to try to go through
this identifying all of our states.
Now the reason why we do this is so
that way we can figure out what's
being oxidized, what is being
reduced within the given problem.
So if I look at the first
one, right, I have iodine two.
That is the natural state of
that particular compound, right?
The diatomic 7, the 7
diatomics, I2 is one of them.
Then what we go to is our next one.
We have OCL minus.
So overall, it has a negative charge.
So what we gotta go through is
thinking of all of our different
rules that we have above.
Right?
The first one is that oxygen is always
negative, is usually negative 2.
So what that means is chlorine
must be positive 1 in order
to make the overall negative.
Then we're going to go to the next one.
So the way that I kind of, one way
I like to do these is I like to
make like a little chart under each
of these species, so that way I
can help assign oxidation states.
So if we kind of think, right, oxygen
is negative two, so that means overall
we have an entire negative six for
all three oxygens that are there.
So this helps us do the math in
our head for what's iodine, right?
So in this case, iodine must be plus
five in order to make the entire
thing equal to the negative one.
that's there for the charge.
Um, and then chlorine
is already negative one.
All right, so now what we are going to
be doing here is we can now try to label
which elements are getting oxidized.
What's getting reduced?
So we're looking for anything
that's changing values.
So when we kind of look, right,
we can see the iodines, right?
It goes from 0 to plus 5, meaning
it's becoming more positive.
So that means it is losing electrons.
So that is being oxidized.
So specifically, iodine is being oxidized.
Now, when we go to the next one, we're
looking for another species, and we
can see the chlorines, right, are going
from positive to negative, so we'll
label those ones as well, right, so
positive to negative, being more negative
means that chlorine is being reduced.
So our other question was all about,
oh, can we label, uh, what's actually
our oxidizing and reducing agents?
And we could do that now.
So keep in mind, it's kind of
like trying to identify the
chaos agent in, in these cases.
So whenever we say chaos agent,
that means they're causing chaos.
So when we label oxidizing agent,
it's what's causing oxidation.
Same thing with the reducing agent.
It's what's causing reduction,
meaning they're a pair.
So in this case, if I have iodine,
iodine I2 is going, is being oxidized.
However, it's causing the reduction.
So that makes it the reducing agent.
It's like the opposite when we're
looking at each of these pairs.
So in that case, being that chlorine is
being reduced, So that means that OCL, in
this case, is the oxidizing agent, okay?
So that is how we would label them,
being it's all about what they
are causing in a given reaction.
Alright, let's take a look at
our next part where we're going
to write our half reactions.
Alright, so now we're going to be writing
our two half reactions, which is based
on what's being oxidized and reduced.
So, first we'll write down that we'll
have our I2, right, so being that
this one is being oxidized, we're
going to match it with its partner.
So we have IO3, aqueous, and that's
going to be one of our half reactions.
Then we'll do the same thing for
OCl minus aqueous, and we can write
that that's going to go to chlorine.
Now for this part, you could potentially
ignore labeling things that are oxidized
and reduced because it's all about
like which ones are matching the best.
But it's always safe to try to
label everything to make sure
you do match it correctly.
Especially if you're relatively
new to oxidation risk reduction.
Generally, these problems always ask
you to label everything, so you should
write down each of the different pairs.
Okay, so we have our oxidized,
and then we have our reduced pair.
Now, what we're going to be doing
for the next step is we're going to
be balancing everything, all atoms
that are not hydrogen or oxygen.
So what you need to now do is you got to
look at your two half reactions and see
is there anything that we can, that's not
hydrogen or oxygen, that's imbalanced.
So if you look at the top one, we
can see that the iodines, right, they
are currently not balanced, right?
We have I2 on the left.
So we're just going to treat
it like a normal problem, uh,
like a normal balancing problem.
And we're going to put a coefficient of
two in front of it to balance our iodines.
Now keep in mind the O's are not
balanced and you can maybe even notice
that there's no oxygens on the left.
So that's where the acid
balancing comes into play.
Now if you look at the bottom, right,
you can see your chlorines are good.
Oxygens are not, so this is where
it's going to go into our next
step, where we're going to balance
things in the following order.
We're always going to do what I
refer to as other atoms, right?
So that was like our iodines.
Then we're going to do oxygen,
then hydrogen, then the electrons.
So let's go to our next step, and
what we're going to do is we're
going to, we're going to do this
just for one of the halves for now.
And then we'll do the other one in
that entire order in one straight shot.
So let's start with the iodine
and go through our steps.
Okay, so our fourth step, we're going
to be balancing the other elements.
So we're going to start
with oxygen, then hydrogen.
So the way that we balance our oxygen is
we're going to be adding water to the mix.
Meaning that for every oxygen that
you have present, we have to add
a water in order to balance it.
So, like, on the right hand side, right,
I have a total of six oxygens that
are there, because I have two IO3s.
So what does that mean is that I
have to add six waters to the left
hand side in order to balance it.
Now, why water?
Why am I doing that?
Well, it's all about the problem, right?
So notice how it says acidic solution.
So what does that mean is
solution, solvent, solute.
The solvent is water, right?
So this is something that's occurring
in water and there's going to
be acid involved, meaning that
there's going to be protons that
are going to be floating around.
So not only do I add water, but I
also have to balance those hydrogens
I just added by adding protons.
So being that I added six waters,
that means you added six hydrogens.
So I'm going to balance that by
adding 12 hydrogens to the other
side in order to balance this.
Okay.
Now this brings us to our
next step is when we add
electrons to balance the charge.
So what does that mean?
Well, the whole idea of oxidation
reduction in order to have a
balanced oxidation reduction.
It's a charges need to be balanced
on the reactants and product side.
So if I kind of like look at all
these species that are on the
left, right, all these are neutral.
So what you can see is everything on the
left, it has a total of a zero charge.
But if I kind of look at the
right hand side, I have positive
ions, I have negative ions.
This is something where if I add
up all the charge, right, I have
a total of 12 plus just from the
hydrogens alone and then two negative.
from the iodates.
So what that means is I have a total
of 10 plus on the right hand side.
That is clearly not balanced.
So what we are going to do is
we're going to add electrons
in order to balance the charge.
So I added 10 electrons.
And what that's going to do is that's
going to then cancel out to also
be zero, because remember, it's all
about electrons being transferred
from one side to the other when
we're kind of doing these problems.
So now what we're going to be doing for
the next part is we're going to be doing
this for the other half reaction as well.
So we completed our iodate.
That's all of our steps for that part.
Let's do the same thing for the other.
So we didn't forget about
the other half reaction.
I just wanted to show you with one
half first, just so we don't have
a million things on the page at one
time, because these are big problems.
So we're going to now do the exact same
thing, but a little bit quicker, right?
So remember the order, other atoms first.
Then oxygen, hydrogen, electrons.
So just in that order.
So, other, O, H, E.
Kind of remember that.
Alright, so chlorines are
other atom, they're balanced.
We're already done that step.
Next one is we're going to balance
our oxygens by adding water.
So on the left hand
side, I have one oxygen.
So what do I got to do?
I got to add one water.
to the left.
Now, being that I added that water,
I got to also now balance my protons.
So I'm going to add two
protons to the left hand side.
And now what we're going to do is
we're going to check our electrons,
right, which was our overall charge.
So I can see on the right
hand side, I have negative one
because I have that one chlorine.
And then on the left, I have two protons,
so two plus, and then a negative.
So that means I have a total of Plus one.
All right.
So that, what does that mean is how
do I get them to be equal being?
I need to add my electrons.
So the only way to do that is if I
add two electrons to the left hand
side, that will now make this entire
left side negative one as well.
So this will be our half reaction for
the reduction side of the problem.
Now let's put it all together.
Our next part is all about
canceling the electrons, right?
You've never seen a chemical reaction
where the electrons are listed in the
reaction, so we have to cancel them.
Now the only way that's possible is
when we multiply these half reactions by
some kind of factor to get the electrons
to be equal in the top and the bottom.
First thing is, before you
kind of go anywhere, is
always double check your work.
Make sure that there are
electrons on the left and the
right hand side of the equation.
If they're on the same side, that
means you did something wrong when
it came to calculating your charge.
Um, same thing with hydrogens,
generally they're on the opposite side
as well, so double check that too.
So in this case, like you see that
we have 12 on the, on the right, on
the top one, and then 2 on the left.
So what we need to do is
we need to make them equal.
So being that the bottom is a smaller
number, What we're going to do is we're
going to multiply the bottom by 5.
So, therefore be 5 times 2 electrons.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to rewrite the
bottom times everything by 5.
So I have 10 electrons, I'll
have 10 protons, then I'm going
to have 5 OCL minus, right?
I'm going to have five chlorines, and
then we will also have five waters that
we're going to have on the problem.
Okay, so we multiplied everything by five.
Now, so what that means is we can kind of
get rid of this entire thing on the top.
We don't need it anymore,
so we'll get rid of that.
All right.
So now what we'll do is we can now put
the two equations next to each other.
And this is where our next step
is going to come into play.
Okay.
So our last step, what we're going to be
doing is we're going to be adding things
together, almost like a math problem.
We're going to add together the two
half reactions, and then we're going
to cancel anything out that's matching
on the left and right hand side.
So like, for example,
the get canceled, right?
So we have 10 electrons on
the right, 10 on the left.
So something like that is going
to end up getting cancelled.
Now what else is going to get cancelled
is anything else that matches.
So notice how we added waters
and hydrogens to the mix.
Those are things that we're looking for.
So we had five waters on the right.
We had six on the left hand side.
So what does that mean is that
we're going to end up reducing that
coefficient down to one, right?
So five into six, we'll
have one left over.
Same thing with the hydrogens, right?
So I'm going to cancel all of the
ones that are on the left hand side.
And as a result, we're only going
to have two hydrogens that are
going to be remaining on the right.
So now what we're going to do is
we're going to take everything and
add it together into one big reaction.
And that's going to be our final answer
is going to be our balanced reaction.
So right.
We have.
One water, and this is the kind of
the part to be careful with, make
sure you're getting everything.
It's so easy to actually
miss something, right?
We have our iodine, then we have our
5 O C L minus, and that's all going
to be everything that's on the left.
Now we have our two iodates, 5 O 3 minus,
and that's aqueous, and that's going to
be added to our five chlorines, and then
the only thing left is our two hydrogens.
Right, so put them back in their green,
and that shows that we have our acidic
component in the reaction as well.
And those are going to be aqueous as well.
So that is our entire balance process.
It was very long, right?
It's a lot of steps.
So let's take a look and
summarize all what we just did.
All right, that's our video, right?
So this is all those different
steps that we had to go through.
And you could see that it was a lot,
right, especially when we started
with the following unbalanced
equation and we balanced it.
So one of the things that I would
really recommend is kind of just, it's
really boils down to just a few steps
is first you write your half reactions,
then balance it other atoms first,
then oxygen with water, then hydrogen
with protons, and then balance your
charge electrons and then combine them.
It's very procedural.
It takes practice with anything.
But you can do this.
Um, if you can conquer this,
arguably, this is probably one of the
hardest things you have to achieve
in general chemistry, one or two.
That does not involve a lot of math.
So especially in terms of
balancing, this is probably the
most difficult balancing process.
But if you can do these, you can
really handle any type of balancing.
Okay, well, thank you
so much for listening.
And if this is your first time here,
please hit that like button, subscribe
to the channel to keep helping it grow,
help reach more students just like you.
And thank you so much for being here.
I really appreciate it.
And if you have any questions, please put
them in the comment section below or send
me a message if you're one of my students.
All right.
Thank you so much.
And I'll see you all later.
Bye now.